Welcome back to AM Northwest. Did you
know canes used to be a fashion accessory
and status symbol? Here to share his
interesting collection, we welcome back
antique appraiser Gary Gurmer. Gary,
great morning. Good morning. >> Okay, now
is this your own collection or so? >>
Oh, no. This is an estate we're working
on. And this is a sampling of over 200
this guy had put together came. Yeah,
it's crazy. Wow. And um and so they
graciously said I could play show and tell
with everybody on the show. >> I love
it. Okay. And I did not know I thought
they were actually used to help people
walk. >> Well, you think that today the
medical and may may have been a little
bit that way, but back in the 18th and
19th century, they were a status and it
would show they told a story as to who
you were and they all had a little bit
different meanings. It's a lot like
wearing a Rolex or a high expensive watch
that a man would have today. It just
made a statement about about your your
wealth or your job. I mean, for this my
favorite one of all of them, but >> Okay,
tell me about this one. >> Well, it's
a it's an actual draw pole uh
um uh telescope or spy glass,
so you could sit in the park and watch
the pretty girls across the park, I
guess, but not for birds. But this would
have probably been a ship's captain's,
you know, or somebody or an engineer
maybe would have would have told a little
bit of a story about his life. And it's
actually a 19th century has the end
caps. You can see through an ebony
one. >> The next one would have been a
doctor, you know. >> Oh, look. Okay.
Can you see that? Maybe it might better
this way. >> You see that on there? It's
a carved little head and has all the
little pressure points. And if you need
to I guess >> acupuncture deal with
someone's head. >> Acupuncture points.
Oh my gosh. Isn't >> that fun? >> Yes.
>> The next one would be a travelers.
That's actually a shark uh vertebrae
that's been out. >> Yeah. And has a
little metal rod down the middle. And they
are that would have been again a sailor
or a ship's captain, somebody who
traveled a lot as as well. >> So it's
easy to pack and all that. >> Well, it
just kind of it's very exotic. And same
with the the lapis one. That's the blue
one. >> The blue one. Let's Okay. >>
Yeah, it it would have been again a real
that's a real status symbol there. It's
carved. It would have been somebody
probably South American and maybe Mexican
or South American, but a very wealthy
person. And it's it was was a real status
symbol to carry that. >> Do you know
anything about the guy
who did the collection?
uh a bit. He was uh he passed away. He
was a a local doctor here. >> Oh, that's
why the interest in the in the medical
thing. Yeah. >> This is one I didn't It's
a stick as far as I know. That's one I
didn't do a lot of research on. I just
thought he had a wonderfully carved head
and um uh and a face. He's just kind
of again, it wouldn't hold up anyone's
weight, but it >> No, he's pretty thin
and light. >> It's something you would
have maybe a theater actor, something
like Do you know like when you go to sell
these how much any of these might sell
for? >> Well, oddly enough, they are
very collectible today and who collects
them are men >> more than women. And
interior decorators like them because they
they they they look good and they're fun
to collect cuz they're not they're not
super expensive. They're not going to
take up your whole house, right? These
range anywhere from simpler ones like
this. This is a very common one. This gold
filled one um would be much more common.
The ebony. This is very typical late
19th century. And this was actually
inscribed to somebody. Sometimes they're 14
karat gold. So if you find one, you
want to make sure it's not goldplated,
>> right? >> And um so something like
that is is is in $150 range. >> Is this
actual ivory? >> No, that is bone. >>
Bone. Okay. >> Yeah. And uh it came apart.
So it is for a traveler. It unscrews in
the middle and then it's handle I think
the handle unscrews as well, but that
would have been um actually for a traveler
and it's stout enough to actually have
been used to help, you know, support the
weight. >> It's solid. Yeah, it's a good
>> really solid. Wow, that's a the work
on this is incredible. Tell me about the
ivory one next to >> this one. Mother
of pearl ebony. This is one where the
What's the old saying about >> ivory? It
was It's pearl. >> Yeah, mother pearl and
and little silver ends. Um it's one of
those things where what's the saying that
says that uh a loaf of bread, a jug of
wine, and thou. You know, if you're out
with your girlfriend and you forgot the
cork screw, you unscrew this
AND INSIDE. >> WOW. OH, >> SO YOU CAN
NEVER BE without this is what you and I
need. >> I'll take that cane [laughter]
from you. Yeah. No, >> a lot of them
have >> You can never be without your
corks. >> Absolutely not. And and a lot of
canes will have the swords are very
common. I he had really Yeah. have a little
rapier sword in it and they
are um very popular obviously.
And it turned out in this collection
his nephews got to him before I did. So
>> Oh, they took those. >> So I didn't
get to bring one. But he did have this
one. And this is actually Mexican
sterling handle. And you open it up
and it has a little gambling spinner.
It looks like a drrele. >> Yeah, it does
look like a drrele, >> but it's called
and it's probably based on a drrele. And
it's called a toma, which means take
it all. >> And so you spin it and you'd
have a a bowl of, you know, everybody
has some co little coins or candies or
something and it says take one,
>> uh, throw one, give one, take one,
give one, and they spin around until
somebody was the one who ended up with
the whole bowl of >> Wow. Wow. And it's a
traditional game. And so >> I'm thinking
now when you say uh designers, home
designers would love this because
it's going to you know a a talk a cons
conversation piece. >> Yeah, absolutely.
>> Like by the fireplace or something
like that, right? >> Right. Exactly. And
I just think I think they're great. And
then um this is Well, look at that. >>
This would have probably been owned by a
uh you know wood carver, right? You
know, or somebody just had their a little
portrait done type of a thing. But it
it's a 19th century with the ivory. Uh,
and it doesn't do anything. And then
finally, this one here is elkhorn.
>> Um,
and I'll try and hold it still. I'm
sorry. Uh, elklororn. Uh, and would have
been like someone that's a very common
material for guys who were hunters,
>> you know, and and they would like it.
And again, this is another one so you
and I can both have one. Oh, >> perfect.
>> Another corkcrew. >> And it looks
like it's a dog. It's been carved out.
The horn has been carved out to be the
face of a dog. >> Yeah. So you have a
hunting your hunting dog >> in your cane.
So this carrying this around would signify
let people know that you were really
serious hunter. >> Wow. You really
come across some really interesting
collections. >> It is. I have >> like mo
the most interesting collection you've
ever >> Well, that's pretty subjective,
but yeah, it's I I just I just started
looking at these and I matter of fact,
I just got them last week from the fell
let me bring them ahead and we're going
to be working on the rest. But I do find
I find these to be fascinating. I just
find and I like I like things you can
collect that aren't going to take
necessarily take up the whole house. And each
of them tells a story. So the rack he
has several racks of them that are uh
they're just fascinating. >>
And also something that's not
made or produced to be a collectible.
>> No. No. I mean there are modern
reproductions you can find, but these
are not. And >> these are originals.
>> And so you get, like I said, they
they're not and they're not horrifically
expensive. I mean, this is probably, you
know, 100 to maybe 150. And this one's
probably the most valuable or the lapis
ones. And they're probably closer to the
thousand range. >> I do love this one
the most. It's incredible. >> Yeah. You
can sit here and >> Yeah. Look around.
>> Spy on your bag down the street.
>> Exactly. Exactly. >> Hey, I'm the
Glattus Kravitz of my neighborhood. I
[laughter] could totally I could totally
>> got to pull the end cap off the
other end. >> Oh, well that would help,
wouldn't it? That's why I'm not seeing
anything. There we go. >> Thanks all the
friends at home. >> Yeah. Oh, there we
go. I can see stuff now. Oh, that's
wild. Love it. I love it. I love it. Gary
Germer, thank you very much. This
was fun. Who knew? Who knew? >> Yeah.
>> All right. Thanks a lot. >>
Thanks. Thank you. >> All right. We'll